Guide to the Algernon Lee Papers TAM.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Algernon Lee Papers
1861-1954
1896-1954
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lee, Algernon
TAM.014
4.5 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes.
Algernon Lee (1873-1954), served as the editor of several socialist publications, including The Worker, The Daily Call, and The New Leader in New York City. He was also the Director of Education at the Rand School of Social Science. From 1909-1954, Lee was one of several Socialist members of the New York City Board of Aldermen temporarily prevented from taking office following his 1919 re-election. Lee also served one term as the national chairman of the Socialist Party following Morris Hillquit's death in 1933. The collection contains correspondence with many leading U.S. and European socialists, published and unpublished writings, radio scripts, ephemera, memorabilia, reading notes, miscellaneous materials and the Civil War letters of Pvt. James Lee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was transferred to NYU from the Tamiment Institute Library of the Rand School of Social Science in 1963. Earlier provenance information is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1962.013.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
For more than 50 years Algernon Lee was a leading figure in the major educational and political activities pertaining to American socialism. After attending the University of Minnesota in the early 1890s, Lee worked as a political organizer for the Socialist Labor Party and served as the editor of several socialist publications, including The Tocsin in Minneapolis and The Worker, The Daily Call, and The New Leader in New York City. In 1909, Lee became the Director of Education at the Rand School of Social Science. He held this position until his death in 1954. In addition to his administrative responsibilities, Lee was also an instructor in economics and American history at the Rand School.
Lee was a member of the New York City Board of Aldermen from 1918 to 1921. As a Socialist Party representative, Lee supported various measures regarding municipal ownership of the transit system and decreases in municipal taxes. During World War 1, Lee, a pacifist, opposed the Board's decision to assist in the sale of war savings stamps, but he later joined the Board in working on behalf of Library Bond sales.
In November 1919, Lee was re-elected to the Board of Aldermen, but was prevented from taking office because he was declared the loser in his race. The Board's committee on privileges investigated the situation and reported that although there had been no election fraud, there were certain "errors" in the vote count which made it appear as if Lee had been defeated in his re-election bid. Upon receiving the committee's report, Lee embarked on a fight to retain his seat on the Board. In November 1921, just two months before his term of office expired, Lee was finally allowed to take office. Lee also sued the City of New York for the $5,500 salary which he claimed was owed to him during this period. Eventually he won this suit with a favorable New York Supreme Court ruling,
Concerning other socialist experiences, Lee was a delegate to numerous Socialist Party national conventions and socialist international conferences. As a Socialist Party candidate, Lee ran unsuccessfully for president of the New York City Board of Aldermen, New York state senator, Mayor of New York City, and other offices. Lee also served one term as the national chairman of the Socialist Party following Morris Hillquit's death in 1933.
During the mid-1930s, Lee was actively involved in the factional disputes which resulted in the Socialist Party split. In 1934, he presided over a Socialist Party rally at Madison Square Garden in New York City which ended in a pitched battle between the Militants and the Old Guard. Unable to hold the various factions together during this turbulent period, Lee withdrew from the Socialist Party in 1936 and joined the Old Guard in establishing the Social Democratic Federation. Lee served as the national chairman and honorary national chairman of the Social Democratic Federation after it was organized. Lee also served on the New York State Executive Committee of the American Labor Party in the late 1930s, but later quit after discovering that the organization was dominated by Communist Party members.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection is comprised of Lee's correspondence, lectures, radio scripts, and writings, described in some detail below, followed by a summary description of the remainder of the collection.
Series I. Correspondence, includes letters from virtually every prominent American socialist as well as many European socialists. Most of the correspondence focuses on the issues involving the Socialist Party, the Rand School, the Social Democratic Federation, the New Leader, the Workmen's Circle, and the American Labor Party. Among the most significant of the approximately 2000 letters in this collection are those from W. J. Ghent. In this correspondence, which spans nearly 40 years, Ghent discusses the Socialist Party's position on World War I, the 1936 Socialist Party split, and other developments and personalities in American socialism. Equally significant for reflections on the socialist movement, particularly on the Socialist Party's formative years and on Norman Thomas, is the correspondence of James Oneal. There are a number of letters from Charles Edward Russell which convey his thoughts on socialist activities and there are several letters from Upton Sinclair which discuss his attitude regarding World War I and his use of George Herron as the model for the hero of World's End. Another interesting feature of the correspondence are four letters which Lee wrote to his wife, Mathilda, describing the events of the 1936 Socialist Party convention in Cleveland. The Lee correspondence also contains important letters from such figures as Morris Hillquit, Victor Berger, Norman Thomas, Meyer London, Eugene and Theodore Debs, Louis Waldman, William E. Bohn, Lena Morrow Lewis, Adolph and Julius Gerber, Abraham Cahan, William Mailly, Harry W. Laidler, and James H. Maurer. Besides the correspondence relating to American socialism, there are numerous letters concerning socialist developments in Europe. Of significant importance within the international correspondence are the letters of Karl Kautsky and his family. These letters describe the deteriorating conditions in post-World War I Europe, the rise of Adolf Hitler, the Kautsky's flight to Holland, Karl Kautsky's death, and the family's eventual move to the United States. In addition to the Kautsky correspondence are letters from Jean Longuet and Raphael Abramovitch. There is also considerable correspondence with several organizations which supported Polish democracy during and after World War II.
Series III. Lectures, pertain to a variety of subjects which Lee presented in his classes at the Rand School. Among the subjects discussed in these lectures are economic history, history of the belief in gods, and the regulation of employer employee relations. There is also a lecture by Alexander Trachtenberg entitled, "Socialism and Trade Unionism" (1916-1917), and a lecture by Harry Elmer Barnes entitled, "The Economic Determination of History: Its Uses, Status and Limitations" (1928), contained in this file.
Series IV. Radio Scripts, which were presented on Lee's weekly program on WEVD, feature commentary and debate on many national and international issues for the period, 1939-1948. Some of the issues discussed in these scripts include labor and socialism, rationing, the release of Earl Browder, the registration of trade unions with the federal government, schizophrenia, the murder of Carlo Tresca, the Harlem race riots, Italian politics following Allied liberation, and the dissolution of the Communist International.
Lee's personal writings in this collection include a diary, speech manuscripts, articles, drafts of pamphlets, position papers, preliminary outlines, memoranda, resolutions, and notes. One of the most interesting items in the Lee Papers is his personal diary (Series V). The diary, which also includes a typewritten transcript, describes reminiscences of Lee's educational activities and his philosophical development from high school onward. Lee's first attraction to socialism at a Nationalist Club in Minnesota is described in the diary, as is his political organizing work for the Socialist Labor Party in Minnesota.
Other writings in this collection are organized into dated (Series VI) and undated (Series VII) items. The dated writings have been given frame numbers for each item and have been cited in the complete reel list. Some of the items in this file include articles on William Morris' view of art, the revolutionary movement in Russian history, the socialist and labor attitude toward war and militarism, Marx's theory of value, military strategy and foreign policy in World War II, and the Socialist International. The undated writings include items on the Rand School classes, the Young People's Socialist League, individualism, educational systems, socialism and farmers, leadership, and the 1934 Declaration of Principles of the Socialist Party.
There is also a small number of pamphlets, articles, statements, memoranda, and newspaper clippings in the ephemeral printed matter (Series VIII). These items include an open letter with which Lee accepted the Socialist Party nomination for Mayor of New York City in 1905, statements and memoranda to the American Socialist Society Board of Directors, position papers on the relationship between the Social Democratic Federation and the New Leader, newspaper clippings on the Social Democratic Federation and other contemporary issues, and a memorial tribute to Lee in 1954. The collection also includes an Account Book (Series II), Autobiographical Materials (Series X), Birthday Testimonials (Series XI), Miscellaneous items (Series XII), and Obituaries and a Last Will (Series XIII).
The only items that were not filmed in this collection were the contents of Series XIV which contains five folders: three folders of Civil War letters written by James Lee (28th Pennsylvania Volunteers, and 147 Pennsylvania Volunteers) to Jane Emerson (1861-1864); one folder containing a narrative of military incidents; and one folder containing some miscellaneous family papers.
Arrangement
Organized into fourteen series:
I. Correspondence
II. Account book
III. Lectures
IV. Radio Scripts
V. Diary
VI. Writings
VII. Undated Writings
VIII. Ephemeral Printed Matter
IX. Reading Notes
X. Autobiographical Matter
XI. Birthday Testimonials
XII. Miscellaneous Items
XIII. Obituaries and Last Will
XIV. Civil War letters of James Lee
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rand School of Social Science Records (TAM 007)
Socialist Alderman Papers (TAM 056.007)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version; microfilm call number is Film R-7124, Reels 58-62. Series XIV is not available on microfilm.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Pamphlets.; Speeches.; Diaries; Account books.; Printed ephemera.; Obituaries.; Wills.; Lectures.; Socialism -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Public opinion; Right and left (Political science).; Clippings (information artifacts); Rand School of Social Science; Bohn, William E.; Social Democratic Federation of America; Lewis, Lena Morrow; Debs, Theodore, 1864-1945; Gerber, Julius, 1862-1916; Ghent, William J. (William James), 1866-1942; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring; Mailly, William, 1871-1912; Maurer, James H. (James Hudson), 1864-; Oneal, James, 1875-1962; Lee, James; London, Meyer, 1871-1926; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933; Kautsky, Karl, 1854-1938.; Emerson, Jane; Gerber, Adolph; Berger, Victor L., 1860-1929; Herron, George Davis, 1862-1925; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Socialist Party (U.S.); WEVD (Radio station) New York, N.Y.; Waldman, Louis, 1892-; United States Labor Party; New Leader (New York, N.Y.: 1924); Russell, Charles Edward, 1860-1941; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968
- Series I: Correspondence, 79807
  - Correspondence, 1898-1915; 79864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Film R-7124, Reel 58, Frame XVI:1
  - Correspondence, 1916-1918; 79863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel xx XVI:1
  - Correspondence, 1916-1918; 79862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1918; 79861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1922; 79860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 58 XVI:1
  - Diary, 1923; 79859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1924; 79858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1925; 79857 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1926; 79856 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1927; 79855 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1928; 79854 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1929; 79853 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1930; 79852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1931; 79851 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1932; 79850 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1933; 79849 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1934; 79848 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1935-Jun 1935; 79847 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1935-Dec 1935; 79846 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1936-Jun 10 1936; 79845 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jun 10, 1936-Dec 1936; 79844 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1937-Jun 1937; 79843 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1937-Dec 1937; 79842 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1938-Jun 1938; 79841 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1938-Dec 1938; 79840 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1939-Apr 1939; 79839 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, May 1939-Sep 1939; 79838 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 59, Frame XVI:1
  - Correspondence, Oct 1939-Dec 1939; 79837 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1940-Mar 1940; 79836 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1940-Jun 1940; 79835 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1940-Sep 1940; 79834 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1940-Dec 1940; 79833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1941-Apr 8, 1941; 79832 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Apr 11, 1941-Jun 18, 1941; 79831 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jun 18, 1941-Aug 1941; 79830 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1941-Dec 1941; 79829 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1942-Apr 1942; 79828 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, May 1942-Dec 1942; 79827 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1943-Mar 1943; 79826 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1943-Jul 1943; 79825 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1943-Dec 1943; 79824 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1944-Apr 1944; 79823 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1944-Aug 1944; 79822 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1944-Dec 1944; 79821 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1945-Apr 1945; 79820 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, May 1945-Dec 1945; 79819 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1946-Jun 1946; 79818 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 60, Frame XVI:1
  - Correspondence, Jul 1947-Dec 1947; 79817 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1947-Jun 1947; 79816 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1947-Dec 1947; 79815 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1948-Apr 1948; 79814 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May 1948-Dec 1948; 79813 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1949; 79812 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950; 79811 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1951; 79810 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1952; 79809 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated; 79808 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series II: Account Book, 1938-1948, 79805
  - Account Book, 1938-1948; 79806 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 61, Frame XVI:2
- Series III: Lectures, 79799
  - Lectures, 1907; 79804 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 61, Frame XVI:3
  - Lectures, 1908; 79803 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Lectures: Socialism & Trade Unionism, ca.1916-1917; 79802 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lectures, 1928; 79801 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Lectures, 1946; 79800 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Scripts, 79789
  - Radio Scripts, 1939; 79798 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Film R-7124, Reel 61, Frame XVI:4
  - Radio Scripts, 1941; 79797 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Radio Scripts, 1942; 79796 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Radio Scripts, 1943; 79795 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Radio Scripts, 1944; 79794 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Radio Scripts, 1945; 79793 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Radio Scripts, 1946; 79792 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Radio Scripts, 1947; 79791 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Radio Scripts, 1948; 79790 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series V: Diary, 25 November 1906 - 4 April 1915, 79786
  - Diary pp. 1-79, 1906-1915; 79788 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:5
  - Diary pp. 80-142, 1906-1915; 79787 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series VI: Writings, 1896-1949, 79773
  - Writings: To the Working People in the Shops and on the Farms of Minnesota, 8 pp., 1896; William Morris on Art, February, 7 pp., 1897, 1896-1897; 79785 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:6
  - Writings: Preliminary Outline for Proposed "Socialist Manual," by W. J. Ghent and Algernon Lee, 9 pp., 1905-1906, 79784 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Writings: Notes on Some Phases of Russian History and of the Revolutionary Movement, 5 pp., 2 February 1907., 79783 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Writings: Papers Written for Carnegie Foundation, 1913; The Attitude of the Socialist and Labor Movement in the United States Toward War and Militarism, 120 pp., 1913, 79782 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Writings: Letters to the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, 3 pp., 1914., 79781 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Writings: The Socialist International Still Lives, 11 pp., 1915, 79780 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Writings: Marx' Theory of Value, 16 pp., June 1928, 79779 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Writings on Workers Education: Paper read to the Board of Directors of the Rand School of Social Science, 5 pp., 8 April 1929, 79778 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Writings: Reminiscences about Alfred E. Smith, 2 pp., 19 October 1930. Projects for a Series of Discussions of Questions of Socialist Principle and Policy, to Be Held Under the Joint Auspices of the Party's Education Committee and the Rand School During the Season of 1931-1932, 2pp., 1931. Comment on Comrade Voorhis' Proposed Leaflet: "What About Agriculture", 4pp. (2 copies), 17 August 1933. Resolution on the discontinuation of the name, "People's Party", for the Social Democratic Federation, 2 pp., 1936. America's Duty Today, 2 pp., October 1939, 1930-1939; 79777 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Writings: Memorandum to the Departments of State and of War, Concerning Desired Sending of American Books to German Nationals in Germany, 8 pp., 1940; War Aims, Peace Terms, and the World After the War, 11pp. (2 copies); 21 April 1941, 1940-1941; 79776 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Writings: Debs and Hillquit, 14pp. (3 copies); 29 August 1944, 79775 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Writings: Paper on "May Day" in 1947, 11 pp., 1 May 1947; Notes on Claessens' Letter to Iverson, 3pp.; 9 July 1949, 1947-1949; 79774 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Series VII: Undated Writings, 79756
  - The Work of the Young Peoples Socialist League, undated; 79772 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:7
  - Historic Individualism, undated; 79771 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - International Workingmans Association, undated; 79770 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Challenge of Social Democracy, undated; 79769 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Notes on Educational Systems, undated; 79768 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Socialism and the Farmer, undated; 79767 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Misc: mostly Rand School notes, undated; 79766 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Misc: 1, undated; 79765 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Misc: 2, undated; 79764 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Misc: 3, undated; 79763 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Misc: 4, undated; 79762 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Misc: 5, undated; 79761 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Misc: 6, undated; 79760 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Misc: 7, undated; 79759 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Misc: 8, undated; 79758 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Misc: 9, undated; 79757 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: Ephemeral Printed Matter, ca. 1898- ca. 1954, nd, 79754
  - Lee: Undated Printed Material, 1898-1954, undated; 79755 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:8
- Series IX: Reading Notes, 79751
  - Reading Notes, undated; 79753 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:9
  - Reading Notes (Part 2), undated; 79752 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series X: Autobiographical Matter, nd, 79748
  - Autobiographical Matter, undated; 79750 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:10
  - Autobiographical Matter, undated; 79749 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Series XI: Birthday Testimonials, 1923-1949, 79746
  - Birthday Testimonials, 1923-1949; 79747 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:11
- Series XII: Miscellaneous, 79744
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1914-1957, undated; 79745 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:12
- Series XIII: Obituaries and Last Will, 79742
  - Obituaries and Last Will, 1954; 79743 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 62, Frame XVI:13
- Series XIV. The Civil War Letters of James Lee, 79737
  - Civil War letters from James Lee (28th Pennsylvania Volunteers, and 147 Pennsylvania Volunteers) to Jane Emerson, 1861-1864; 79741 (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
    Not Microfilmed
  - Miscellaneous family papers, undated; 79739 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Narrative of military incidents, including transcription, undated; 79740 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Letter to Miss Florence Lee, undated; 79738 (Box 9, Folder 11)